foreign
what's the aim what is your aim
and then the response is usually well
freedom from suffering but what do you
mean by
suffering that you're trying to be free
from and what would
Freedom me
right oh yeah so what is suffering
basically yeah what what understand by what are
yeah what what understand by what are
you trying to escape yeah
because uh
the reason a mind suffers is because the
mind doesn't understand suffering it's
not because my mind experience is
suffering but of course everybody starts by
but of course everybody starts by
non-understanding so
firstly you experience suffering you
want to get rid of it you want to deal
with it you want to seek you want to
practice you want to just do something
about it
uh but then yes if if you have come
across the right instruction then you
will you should be realizing gradually
that right that which I'm trying to get
rid of that suffering that pain actually
needs to be understood in order to get
rid of it
so then do I understand some what is
suffering for me
so when I experience discomfort what is
where is that suffering is it just
State of Mind state of the feeling both
neither in between have I understood
what suffering is
because I'm you know I'm I feel
justified in being preoccupied
and and constantly seeking the answer
and practice to get rid of it but as I
said if you actually start reading the
suit as closely you realize getting read
means understanding that's how you
abandon it
not not having it
so what is there that needs to be
understood
so what is suffering yeah let's start
with that
and mental anguish pressure
but in terms of Anguish and
stress is a stress mental stress so
um
can you have a pleasant feeling
experience through senses and so on but
mentally suffer an account of it
can you have an unpleasant feeling but
mentally not suffer I'll encounter it
yes to all options exactly yeah yeah so
so then suffering is not in how you feel
which is why we come back to what I keep
saying on and on and on and on
you have to stop feeling take it for
granted and feeling justified in trying
to get rid of your feelings because they
bother you because you're acting out of
the border of the feeling means you're
affirming your assumption your wrong
view that the problem is in the feeling
so where is then that suffering if it's
not in the feeling if if you can
sometimes feel good or bad but not
necessarily suffer see if the suffering
is in the feeling each time you're
experiencing discomfort or feeling not
so good you would also have to suffer an
account to it but the fact that you
don't means it does not actually
match doesn't add up that suffering is
there because otherwise why are you not
suffering
two types of unpleasant feelings so some
are connected with as a bodily State um
you know whatever and others are
connected with I must say well I'd call
them your karma basically it's it's a
result of your unwholesome actions that
that cause sort of distress maybe
remorse and and all this that's it all
the hindrances so well yeah but that's
irrelevant but you can have two types six types
but you can have two types six types
neither of them is the cause of
suffering because if your karma would be
the cause of suffering means you
wouldn't be able to do anything about it
until the karma Runs Out
and as the Buddha said himself that's a
completely wrong view it's a form of
determinism so yes some might be caused by Karma
so yes some might be caused by Karma
some might be caused by what you did
what you thought somehow because by
immediate physical experience some might
be caused by change of elements
those just why they're there but that
doesn't matter because none of them is
the root of suffering
present there isn't cause present there
isn't suffering
and that's exactly the point see people
would be concerned about where their
feelings came from and why because they
still assume that the suffering is in
them or defined by them
so it's the in the broadest terms as we
said so many times before it's your
present enduring attitude to the present
enduring feeling in regard to the
present enduring feeling that's where
the suffering is
so it is possible to be
the same I know enlightened and still uh
suffer on account of your hindrances as
a
no it's possible to be enlightened and
still have this comfort and
uncomfortable feelings coming
true but you wouldn't suffer encounter
them but isn't it like this that the nature
but isn't it like this that the nature
of these feelings uh so the the origin
of the students is changed so they might
be coming from from
um from body but they're not going to
come from from the hindrances so and
this no no well it doesn't matter that's
the point like in that suitable the
Buddha lists those seven or eight things
why because of which one might feel
suffering he was just to tell you basically that
he was just to tell you basically that
it one one of the reasons was
circumstances an accident why one might
feel well when my experience is Comfort
well when my experience is Comfort
feeling yeah sorry not suffering well
why one might feel discomfort and
experience uncomfortable feelings change
of the elements change of the bile and
so on previous comma was just one of the
reasons in other words the whole point was like
in other words the whole point was like
yes they will have a reason to be there
the reasons might change but if feeling
was not a problem to start with
why it is there and what reasons are
behind it are equally not a problem
and feeling is not a problem
the root of suffering is not feeling
it's not one surface because one feels
no one suffers because one craves
and one craves in regard to what one
feels regardless of why one feels that
or this and where he came from
so present enduring attitude I craving
so it's presently during feeling
regardless of why it came and why and
when for how long and and what caused it
and whether it will be caused again
for how do you start
by upgrading or removing the wrong
attitude or fading away or abandoning
relinquishing overcoming the wrong
attitudes towards whatever you're
currently feeling what would be the
necessary first step
son's restraint and virtue exactly why
because it's none
I mean it's a emulating
the non-craving to to to to
yeah instead of in other words because
nonsense restraint and non-virtue would
always be rooted in craving yeah
whether you know it or not yeah it
requires craving well and that exactly
craving would then perpetuate the
assumptions where the problem is acting
out of craving feeds the assumptions as
to what you should act towards and where
the problem is
so
virtue sense restraint and as we
discussed in previous talks that kind of
starts revealing the
um the intentions the choices on that
mental level
makes it more obvious which is what
starts constituting the development of
the Mind
so if you're not acting by Body by
speech you're now Discerning the
intentions the Leaning the attitudes of
the Mind in regard to this that's felt
or that that is felt you can start
Discerning the difference or at least
distinguishing it
now you can't willingly choose to not
have a certain attitude towards a
feeling so if there is a prospect of
agreeable feeling sensuality uh
safety of some sorts your mind is
delighting in it so what do you do
you get rid of the Delight by denying
the thoughts what do you do how do you
not Delight when the Buddha says he
doesn't Delight in that feeling he
doesn't welcome it how do you do that
how can you do that can you just choose
to not Delight in what the mind is
already delighting in
how did the Buddha do that while he was
still a bodhisatt as he said in that
Sutton okay the danger exactly contemplating
okay the danger exactly contemplating
the context the wisdom that you got an
account of pondering and reflecting so
my mind is delighting in the prospect of
this I can't stop that well but I can't
stop is acting out automatically
habitually and like certainly I can't
provide for this
Untamed mind this Beast that wants to go
and feed in other people's pastures well
I can keep just
talking to it in a sense of providing
the context the danger reminders and it
will have to listen it cannot ignore it
it might not listen instantaneously but
as it would have said he would think
about the Peril the lack of satisfaction
how this is uh not beneficial for me or
for others and dwelling on that context
while the Mind Delights the sensuality
he would stop delighting in it so you
got rid of it
and then Neil will comes thoughts of
Cruelty come sing
you work on the sustaining the con
composing the context the samadhi of the
context of no this is harmful factually
harmful you don't need to be is this
harmful let me look at the etymology of
the word harmful you know it's harmful
results in further engagement further
hassle further proliferation further
repercussions for you for others for
both and every time that you can
remember in the past it always resulted
in the same and that's why even you want
to practice now because on some level
you already know it is not beneficial
for me so hammer that in and keep
hammering that in day and night not
blindly like as some sort of Mantra but
when the Mind Delights to its sensuality
when the Mind leans as the attitude
towards cruelty or thoughts of your will
and so on you provide the context so the
Mind comes down you can't just tell the
mind to come down well eventually you
can when you tamed it then becomes pliable
when you tamed it then becomes pliable
and listens to you
and then you could directly go over
there or go over there or investigate
this don't think about that and it will
listen every single time
because you did the work of taming it
down first
but even then it's not a matter of the
choice that you think choice is now
the way it is it's it's a different
different relationship but yes you have
you have developed it
whereas if you're used to acting out of
it going towards the content then asking
these questions just is harder and
harder and is it less and less
um yeah they become more and more
abstract yeah and they drift away so
that's why like first you have to stop
engaging with it physically verbally you
know bite your tongue if you have to and
not speak and not act
again not just out of some mystical
release they will so that you can
basically start Discerning oh the
context the Mind intentions let me
Ponder on these thoughts uh these
dangers within what mind is delighting
or within what mind is resisting it's
like this uh in mundane sense the
intervention you know
this person is
addicted to something and then the
family gets around and intervenes you
know and tells them look what you're
doing look what is happening yeah and
then maybe for a while he gets the
picture gets the context
goes to rehab whatever but
with yourself you have to that's what
you've got to do with your mind yeah you
know always intervene and the reason why
it's a good example also it's because it
is kind of indirect it's even in mundane
sense the intervention is successful one
when a person starts decides on account
of what you've been telling him it's not
a really successful one when you just
forced into they might do it for as long
as there is a force in applied the
moment that stops they drift back
because the views haven't changed just
understanding is when you've seen the
harm so you you can't I mean you can try
and force your mind but you you can see
what it will lead to the point is no no
you prevent it from making it further
worse further you prevent it from a kind
of aggravating the situation to like
non-restraint and non-virtue then your
work is to just feed in this context and
sustain the context and protect the
context then make sure you don't forget
or choose to willingly distract yourself
from the context and the mind will have
to hear it because it's just that's all
it sees now like that taming delivery
first have to get it out of the wild
forest it's it's sort of perpetuating
its wild behavior and then it will kick
and scream when he comes down then okay
well here's the food here is it oh it
starts taking food starts listening
starts recognizing me okay now stand up
move down do this this all of that it's
on the level of making the Mind turn
away from things that are unbeneficial
for the mind and for you
but you can't force it you can't
magically have something that will just
result in the physical oh how did I get
there anyway it doesn't matter this must
be what nibana is no you you train it
away from it
gradual training and then it will listen
to you and then if the Mind listens to
you through perpetually feeding the
context sustaining the context whether
you're sitting walking going to the
toilet or whatever else then you won't
have to feed that context as much and
that's exactly what I said oh wait now
my mind is not going back to these
things I'm not getting these thoughts it
doesn't Delight in sincerity anymore
there is no more cruelty or I could rest
now I don't need to be constantly
working on the context in the two types
of thought okay so let me now study this
mind internally no work to be done if
sensuality comes coming back again or
real will well okay I know what to do
the context bring it back until the Mind
comes down
and that's what led into first John
coming down within the right context of
thinking and pondering that the mind has
withdrawn from
this context is basically understanding
beneficial and beneficial the context is
always in regard to where your mind is
leaning it's not a universal sort of
thing that's our context counting oh
first where is what's the state of the
mind now what's what what are you
currently feeling what is your attitude
towards what you currently feel are you
with the lighting are you resisting are
you fearing it context in regard to that
every single time whenever there is a
feeling present you gotta work on the
context in regard to it otherwise you'll
be conflating feeling for your suffering
whereas if you're
um acting out of sensuality or will
um distraction your what is in front of
you you cannot establish the context
because you're always changing what's in
front of you yeah so or at least hoping
that it will result in changing what's
in front of me which just perpetuates
the view that you think the problem was
there in front of you so you're not
allowing that thing to endure to then be
able to establish reveal your attitude
of like whether their mind is delighting
or resisting and so on you won't see the
signs of your mind if you don't let
things in you're on that mental level
yeah
are there any means how one can
accelerate this process so well but
probably the first mean would be the
question you need to ask yourself why
would you want to accelerate it well I
mean it's obvious they say we have
finite life and ends better
whether you believe yeah but no what
makes you think that already the
practice is not fast enough or something
why do you want it to be even faster is
it because it's not happening
well because you still suffer
so in a way yes if you understand
suffering thoroughly right here and now
you'll be another hunt Right Here and
Now so means of accelerating the process
are not on the level of process
they're on the level of understanding
so if you are if you're coming from a
point of view of a method other things
that I can do to speed this up no
if you're coming from a point of view of
determination to understand Clarity and
protecting the context yes and that's
exactly what you do but even then you
can't say how fast it will be the Buddha
couldn't say how fast it would be he
said if somebody practices upon their
right to view their practices four
foundations of mindfulness correctly
well it might take seven days seven
weeks seven months seven years or what a
half half a night if they do it rightly
uh in the same sense he gave the simile
of the the carpenter with an ax
he uses it he works on it he's not
concerned about how quickly the handle
is wearing wearing thin
but he knows it has to wear thin because
I'm using it so if your concern is on
the acceleration means you're kind of
not seeing it on the level of
understanding if you're seeing on a
level understanding consideration
wouldn't bother you because you wouldn't
have craving in regard to the speed of
your freedom from craving
so there was this example from
um of um whenever Ananda who could not
well wasn't enlightened or wasn't
another hunt but and he was trying to
accelerate it basically and then and he
was even reproached that instead of
meditating he was sort of soothing the
the people's
pain because of the demise of the Buddha
so apparently or would you say that if
he didn't meditate then he was he wasn't
really sustaining this attitude so that
he needed to really to sit in order to
to make progress I don't I don't quite a
tank you say it again so
um so apparently he through his
meditation include through his sitting
he managed to accelerate it to the point
that he attained right right right well
again relatively speaking he wasn't the
meditation of the sitting he was
actually walking and it was that did not
accelerate it it was what made him do
that accelerated and what maybe what
made him do that is the fact that he
closest to the Buddha was not allowed
now to join the meeting of arhans
because he's still a trainee so it was a
sense of Shame lack of accomplishment
weakness uh that made him then make the effort
uh that made him then make the effort
and then when he finished walking
meditation and contemplation that's what
walking meditation is it's not doing
make I mean how could it how could you
watching Souls of your feet for example
but people generally would think oh slow
movement how can that reveal the context
of yet you're currently enduring feeling
no only you investigate in that
direction so that's what he did he
protected the context in regard to any
thoughts that had risen there was of the
unwholesome nature he established his
mind upon the nature of an enduring body
for example such as that it's unownable
to the point of souls the top of your
head to the soles of your feet and he
drilled that throughout the night he
protected the context he steady his mind
in it he did not get distracted from it
when he said okay I did what I could do
I have to lay down and rest so be it so
he did and he realized oh I actually
completed all the work so he used the
handle he did not stop to check the
handle am I accelerating this am I
accelerating this no he just used it
used it until his hand went numb and he
just laid to sleep and then realized oh
he wore out the handle
and yeah then he was in our hand but
even then he couldn't tell how much he's
accelerating and the acceleration in
this sense was not his committed sort of
meditation technique he was the sense of
Shame and lack of accomplishment which
was often found in other suitors as well
when a monk was about to kill himself
because he was not free from sensuality
for over 25 years of being in robes and
about to use the knife with a Despair
and anger and frustration
and then that made him practice and take
up the practice correctly and finish the
work and then became another hunt
are full of that because he he basically
seeing the danger you you the danger he
had the right view that's like yeah so
it's not a question he didn't even know
what the dhamma is so and that's why he
felt so ashamed for over 20 years that
he's been with the Buddha he knew what
the work was he was a sought Upon A from
the start yet he didn't do it because he
was too busy distracting himself with
helping these people helping those
people serving the Buddha and all and
and everything else he didn't do his
work I mean the Buddha himself
reprimanded him many times quite harshly
in the suitors
so it's not just a question of he
doesn't have a clue what the practice is
uh and just out of a blue decide that
he's going to sit and meditate and in
the morning he was another hunt and he
knew exactly what the practice was he
just wasn't doing it he was distracting
himself from it so could you say that if
you want to accelerate the work do the
work basically it's more as in well
exactly there is no magical kind of I've
accelerate certain Behavior
they will then result in this no you
accelerate what you know need
acceleration and What needs acceleration
is again protecting the context not
giving uh not uh maintaining
not tolerating the mind that it's sort
of delighting in sensuality having
thoughts of Cruelty having thoughts of
conceit and vanity and so on so yet the
work needs to be done and you could do
it faster more efficiently if the work
is clear
so if you want to accelerate the
progress towards and chip
you need to understand first what
progress the wizardship is in other
words you need to get the right view
become a Sota bana and then you'll know
exactly what to do and if you commit to
it is the Buddha said himself you might
get it in a fortnight you might clear
your mind from any assumption any
resistance to it anything felt within a
fortnight if not at least within seven
years if there is some residue left well
again you wouldn't have to worry
eventually it was about
until you can maybe say
clarify well clarifying the work
clarifying the danger that you're in
clarifying the escape from that danger
clarify making an effort yeah but even
then even then the point is even then
the relationship between your context
your effort the danger the sensory
strength and the mind development it's
not the power of I choose one two three
four five and this is the result it
always has that indirect certain aspect
to it
so yes if you really withdraw your
elephant from the Wilderness really use
the leather straps really feed it at the
right time right things it will calm
down quicker
but that's not to say that you can
influence that quickness directly to
make it calm down quicker
trying to make it calm down quicker
would be stopping the work using the X
handle to check is it wearing out
you can't check it while you're using it
so you realize let me stop checking let
me just work and use it
when it runs out I will know it's
liberated as the other hands would say
or is it how much you can't quantify it
in that sense so basically
so basically
um Ananda didn't need to really to do
any practice so well I mean any
say a formal practice so he he just he
could just have stayed I know in his uh
near the boat and and yeah whatever and
this could this would be his meditation
well yeah his meditation is on the level
of the Mind so the meditation is on the
level of uh where the mind inclines what
the assumptions there are so the
practice is to unravel that
disentangle it
abandon the unwholesome cultivated
wholesome so nobody needs to do any
practice in that sense like physically
what you physically need to do is
withdraw yourself from centrality not
act out when you're touched by
unpleasant feeling don't give rise to
actions by body and by speech cultivate
that endurance being able to take it so
you don't act out of it so you see what
the context is behind it
so what physically needs to be done is
withdrawn from acts of sensuality
seclusion uh moderation in eating
and they're not spending all their time
sleeping or distracting yourself with
work or talking with others that's the
extent of physical methods
then the watchfulness the knowledge of
intentions that's no matter what you do
physically I mean the Buddha said you
when he purified his mind and to the
first Jana then
whether he was walking going to the
toilet clearing his bowl eating whatever
he was doing he was divine because the
mind was fully turned away from that
he has surmounted it
and now you know ah so this is how I
accelerate my practice
by providing the suitable food avoiding
the unsuitable food I don't know to what
degree the speed would increase but I
know for sure it will have to go in that
direction so the more suitable food it is the more
so the more suitable food it is the more
I bet the better the withdrawal the more
effort I make into protecting the
context the faster my mind is like the
basically the more I work with an ax
handle the more is wearing out just
factually it's wearing down
if I pick it up once a month well that's
the acceleration rate once a month
if I work with it every single day six
hours a day well I still I can see how
much directly but I know for sure it's
more than once a month
and also another reason why you cannot
directly influence or no acceleration is
because you don't really know
how much that mind needs to be
completely purified
so all you can do is provide a context
and then keep working on it and that's
where it says arahunts would carry on
practicing mindfulness so to speak
because it ceases to be practiced for
them and they will recognize when the
mind is liberated and they will know
liberated mind as liberated mind they
would know or there is no coming back to
what has been liberated from
oh at that point they can drop the
practice but then you realize well
there's nothing for them to drop because
they haven't been doing anything in that
sense of oh I got to stop these duties
now but yeah sense of urgency
but yeah sense of urgency
is an acceleration Factor
fear is an acceleration Factor Divine
Messengers are acceleration factors
so you want to accelerate to practice
ponder about what you're liable to
what's about to happen to your health to
your life
to the loved ones to the things you
possess like inevitable inconceivable
for it to be otherwise yet by ignoring
it you've developed where people
developed this assumption that
it's not going to happen oh no of course
I know it's going to happen but you
don't dwell on it if you dwell on it
then it will sink in that it will happen
and that will be felt differently so
there you go you're gonna have immediate
acceleration but be careful before you start
but be careful before you start
accelerating because you better know
what direction you need to accelerate to
if you still don't even know what the
practice is and then just start
accelerating things well I suppose if
you have enough composure that could
make you then really try to find out
what the practice is but it could also
make you break down so
the two types of two results of being
touched by suffering correctly
Noble search or mental Arrangement
that's exactly what I ended up
describing here
and someone said recently it's also about not
not
infinitely trying to clarify the idea of
what the practice or or what
Enlightenment Enlightenment is
but also asking myself
am I applying myself to the degree to
which I have understood yeah yeah well
that's that other I mentioned it was
yesterday so he he visits the wise men a person
so he he visits the wise men a person
intent upon his welfare oh I better I
better find a way out of this situation
so he visits the wise man he lives he
doesn't look for faults doesn't mean he
accepts everything they say no he he
hears the teaching then he reflexively
Ponders on it then he measures the task
in other words oh it's not just a
question of accepting the view that I
presented you it's exactly what you just
said okay so to this extent this is what
I do this is how I apply myself this is
what I don't do with the pre this let me
do it and see whether it it uh it brings
some sort of
information of that this is the right
practice and so on but it is through
doing you you can then find out but not
allow this is pleasing to me that's not
accepted I don't this is displeasing to me
I don't this is displeasing to me
because I don't like how he looks thus I
don't accept it
that's not wisdom let me compare
let me go to the other wise man and the
other wise man and the other wise man
you can compare everything and see which
one is if you like Clarity of as to what
you need to really apply you can compare
but exactly then you could equally lose
perspective and end up being just
revolving around comparisons and drawing
parallels and similarities and oh yeah
the two factors from here respond to
five and this is it are you applying any
of that
if so is there a measurable kind of
freedom from suffering felt experienced
Clarity in regard to okay now if there
is no access to information if there is
no access anymore to any suit any
teaching any questions and answers would
I know exactly what to do and if I stick
to it complete freedom from suffering
Here and Now within seven days seven
months seven years
do I know that
huh seven lifetime or seven items sure
but you don't necessarily see that right
like even solomonas needed to be told
that by the Buddha but this you would
see no this is the way out I'm sure already
no this is the way out I'm sure already
do I see it and if there is no more
distractions uh or other input if I were
to stick to with this free me from
suffering do I have such knowledge
knowing the way out basically and that
sorta party knowing the way out that's
why it says in the suttas one who
becomes he's like uh he's beyond the
instruction from anybody else he's
beyond the the changes in the views of
the world and he's certainly Beyond uh
following any other teacher in a sense
even if the entire world says oh the
Buddha was wrong well he knows that the
entire world is wrong
because on account of understanding what
the Buddha instructed he himself Here
and Now
sees the complete freedom from suffering
but then yeah he can become negligent
distracted and so on because he's kind
of free on one level certainly from
photogenous point of view which is why
the complacency can set in and that's
why they wouldn't need it to constantly
remind the the noble disciples that
there is still work to be done thus do
it because you can it's right there
or if some external circumstance
prompted him such as the Buddha is
passing away the despair the shame oh
okay now there's really nothing else
worth of my time see that's what Ananda
felt he felt
serving the Buddha being around the
Buddha was a justifiable distraction
because as far as the distractions go it
was pretty justifiable but there isn't
it in a wrong view sorry isn't isn't it
a wrong view which one that that there
is just a file of Destruction
uh not necessarily like a wrong view in
terms of not knowing what the way out of
suffering is it's a it's a certainly an
impediment a distraction is distraction
that's why sodapan is not an arachanta
doesn't have the wrong views but he
still has the hindrances he still has
the distraction he still has degree of
lost aversion conceit
so I'm going to say it's the wrong view
I would say it's a you can have it with
the Right View that has not been fully
developed those are the residues the
distraction the last the the the
irritation the hindrances only other
Hunt is beyond has destroyed hindrances
I mean it's it's a false false
conception which one well that that
there is something which is worth of
distracting myself so basically no it's
a relative I wouldn't say it's false as
I said as far as the distractions go
serving the Buddha
its least harmful distraction but yes
from an arahan's point of view or one
one who wants to be in our hand it's a
distraction which is why the Buddha kept
telling him off as well to not distract
himself
but if if that were to be on the level
of the view then there would be no Noble
disciples that understood the path but
haven't fully developed it would be
either you have a wrong view you know
nothing and you have a right view you
are an arahunt but there is the whole
area in between which is often why
people can't understand how can satapana
not want to practice for nibana become
distracted from it engage with
sensuality well that's how
it's not on the same level you got the
overall view the freedom the way out but
now you got to do it now you've got to
protect your mind from unwholesome I
mean the Buddha gave
I don't know maybe not hundreds but many
similes exactly like I would come and I
would pull the arrow out of the wound
the surgeon would come and do that and
tell listen good man I pulled the arrow
no more poison left but the wound is
still there it will take time for it to
heal if you wanna accelerate its healing
eat the right food don't eat the wrong
food cover it up don't expose it to dust
and the Sun and so on but then that man
would expose it to the dust expose it to
the Sun eat the unsuitable food food the
wound would get infected and he would
suffer on account of it and then give
exactly that's how somebody gets the
Right View pulls the arrow ignorance
that the poisonous humor of craving and
so on but factually the Mind still needs
time to tame down but then they go into
unsuitable things attend to unsuitable
things distract themselves so they perpetuate
distract themselves so they perpetuate
the wound unnecessarily
that's the difference here
so can London say that is
um has let's say Right View with regard
to the practice but he might have lots
of wrong views regarding
um
um well maybe even regarding the
hindrances uh
uh
well no see again it's not
the views you're talking about so right
view is not on the level of opinion
about the practice
Right View is the existential attitude
now sure within an existential latitude
of right kind or wrong kind you can have
many irrelevant views
like sodapana can have many views on
other things they have nothing to do
with the practice
or they're a secondary to it
but fundamentally he's right the nature
of the right view it means that it's not
on the level of the same level as wrong
views and opinions or generally ideas
that people would have
it's the view that basically has
uprooted the atavada in regard to any
view you might have
so it's not just over there comparable
so they might be ignorant about like
some worldly thing well they might be
ignorant about the uh those like more
more detailed aspects of the dhamma of
the Buddha's instruction because they
haven't done it long enough they haven't
pondering long enough but they cannot be
ignorant about with this this is about
the nature of not self about where the
true uh cause of suffering is and where
the true escape they can't be ignorant
about that it says he sort of could
engage in sensuality but if he had to
ask himself or look is this good
beneficial we wouldn't need to oh yeah
yeah but then he couldn't do it yeah
because well that's the thing so what
sodabana can do is turn a blind eye to
his right existential attitude of the
Right View and that's like when people
did become soda pandas and then okay but
you know let me go and you know home
mother wives I have to look after
as in their content now with that deeper
understanding of where the Escape is
because see you can be in the prison and
it's what it's really frightening is you
don't know the way out like really you
don't know the way out it's just you're
completely entrapped and then you find a
way out
you fully and even the gods are not
aware of it nobody's aware of it and you
can see it and you can go halfway up and
come back but you're not leaving the
prison yet because it's going to be a
bit unpleasant to crawl through the way
out and also you got some friends and
people you need to help in here
before you God because if I go out
you're on your own you don't exist for
me anymore
but I want to help they help me here before
I want to help they help me here before
I knew the way out or whatever children
dependence and so on
so they postponed the way out that is
going nowhere and that's another sense
of safety where it comes from
sothapana's Right View it's not going
anywhere and that's exactly why they can
and that's exactly why they can
procrastinate and and that like I think
the first time it is like but how can
they because the idea of Enlightenment
is just this experience and he's just
Bloom done finished there's nothing in
between but then you have the Buddha
constantly the pre-minding man's foot
monks for not completing the work but that's
for not completing the work but that's
how you not complete the work you know
where the work is it requires we're
doing but there is something else
keeping you to this
justifiable not some ridiculous serving
robes yeah when they were solving robes
and spreading the order and teaching the
the nuns and all of that but at the same
time have you escaped all the way out
you got to put that first
and and that's that's exactly what I'm
that's exactly the difference here
and see now although Assad will choose
to stay in that prison there is no more
fear there is no more dread and Terror
from the gods from from not knowing the
Escape because oh you know this cape and
not just that you know the Escape you
know that you know the escape and
anything that could block that escape
does not even know about the Escape
so it's a it's an internal uh Dimension
between you and Escape that nobody not
anything in the world there was brahmas
anything can come in between
so yeah it's pretty much quite an
immeasurable confidence but you do have
to start crawling up that escape
eventually and Ananda did when there was
no more justifiable reasons for him to
stay in the prison
paired with all the shame that he felt
in account of our hands dismissing him I
mean gospel is quite blunt some might
say rude
a number of occasions calling him young
boy and stuff like that he says we call
me young boy I have gray hairs and it's
completely disrespecting him
because he's not doing the work
not that he doesn't know where the work
is he's just distracting himself and
from somebody's point of view like who
was like
the foremost austere determinations John
as it will
hemp probes rough forests refusing any
comfort yeah you could see why he was
talking the way he was talking
so it was quite a contrast
seven days he says yeah
seven days he was done too long
when the Buddha called him and says hey
come on you finish your work you're old
now like getting on like while living in
the rough forests and wearing rough
robes and living of poor food I get
plenty of robes I get plenty of
dwellings coming you can partake in this
because you did the work he says no no
whoever contain John as a will and all
these states of mind it will this is
this is heaven this is so pleasant and
it would appraise him for practicing for
the future generation not for him
for the future as in like it's inspiring
but he's doing it's inspiring